Supply and demand is an incredible
concept. But just like any other concept
in trading, sometimes it fails.
Fortunately, with supply and demand, a
failure can actually provide a whole new
opportunity. And there's even a way to
see them coming before they happen. I'm
going to be teaching you all about
supply and demand fails, how to spot
them early, and how to trade them
successfully. Let's get to it. So, if
you're new to the concept of supply and
demand, or you kind of understand it,
but you don't really understand the
theory behind it, we're going to break
that down now. Supply and demand refers
to price areas in a market where
significant buying or selling has taken
place. Now, this is what we call a
demand zone. It's a little box that we
can draw on the chart. And what this
demand zone shows is an area where
significant buying has entered the
market. This impulse shows clear buying
control from this level up to where the
market is now. We know it shows clear
buying control because there are these
large bullish candles and not really too
much in the way of seller or bearish
strength. So this shows a very strong
push from buyers. Now the demand zone is
the area just before this impulsive
move. What a demand zone shows is the
area where all of this buying began.
Now, in the flip example where we'd be
looking at a supply zone, it's simply
the same, but instead we're looking at
an area where supply is stepping into
the market. So, lots more units being
sold in. When we see a area before a
large downward move, this shows us that
this area of consolidation, this
sideways move, this is where the selling
has kicked in. So, therefore, this is a
premium price to sell your assets. If
the market gets back to it, we'd be
looking for other traders to sell assets
at this level either through uh
obligatory buyback later contracts like
short positions or just through profit
taking as well. So supply and demand
essentially shows prices that buyers and
sellers are happy to pay for assets. And
what we're looking for is a
follow-through of that willingness to
buy at these levels once the market
returns to them. It's very simple stuff.
So that's the theory behind supply and
demand. The next thing we need to cover
is just how we draw these zones. And
this one's really quick. For me, I use
the last candle before the impulse. So,
in this example, we can see this is a
indecision candle. There's wicks, tiny
candle body. No real movement has been
made throughout that candle. But the
next candle is a very large impulsive
candle with clear buying control. The
candle body is large. It's made a
significant movement one way. That is
the impulse candle. So, the last candle
before the impulse is going to be the
one we have marked on here. Now in a
selling example again it would just
simply be the final consolidation candle
before the large downward move that
becomes the supply. The reason I look at
it like this is because this is the
final exact point before major
distribution took place. Okay. So that's
how I mark them. The last candle before
the impulse. Now like all concepts in
trading these supply and demand zones
are sometimes just going to fail.
They're not going to work. They're not
going to hold. This example we have a
demand zone here. we have another demand
zone which is far beneath all the way
down here. Now, this is the last candle
before the impulse that still has
imbalance into it. So, if we're looking
for a reversal, we're going to be
looking for that around this point.
Sometimes, as I've said, these zones
simply will not hold. And if we run this
market forward, you'll see that the
market has pushed through this low. Now,
what this does is creates what we call a
demand fail, which is coming in around
this point. And this gives us an
indication that this market could
potentially be ready to go lower. So
this is where demand and supply fails
actually become valuable to us. Rather
than just losing a trade and not having
any other opportunity, what we have here
is possibility to now say, well, if this
demand hasn't worked, we haven't seen
the buying pressure we wanted to see
come in here. Now, we may go lower
towards the next demand, which allows us
to then potentially look for short
opportunities down to this point because
this demand failing and the ability to
push lower that we've seen in the market
is showing seller control coming in. So,
we could look for pullbacks to higher
areas of supply. We have two core ones
in this range. This one here and this
one here. And we may see this as
potential to sell down into the area of
demand given that we've seen this first
demand fail. the next logical kind of
magnet point for the market to get to
and then potentially react from is going
to be the lower demand zone down here.
Okay, so that's something we can
actually utilize, take advantage of, and
potentially find opportunities from.
Now, you'll see this market ran all the
way up, not reacting to the first zone,
but filling the second zone, which could
potentially provide a trade in itself.
Now just as a hypothetical position you
can see that by selling from here we may
have then grounds to take the market
down to the next zone. Right? So what we
can actually do when it comes to supply
and demand failing is find somewhat
shorterterm opportunities against the
initial direction we were looking for.
When we first came in to this demand, we
would have been looking for a reversal
to take this market higher. But given
that it failed, we then see, okay,
buyers evidently are no longer in
control in the way that we thought they
were. What that is likely to do is see
seller control continue until we meet
another high interest area. The next
high interest area will be the next area
of demand. And as we see, when the
market pulls back and hits a supply
zone, we then get grounds to sell from
there and target the next magnet point.
So you can see we actually find
opportunity within supply and demand
fails. If a demand doesn't work, it then
tells us, okay, we're no longer looking
at buyer control, we're looking at
seller control. And then when we see
that break, we can find opportunity to
sell and use these next demand zones or
swing lows or we'll look at a couple
different examples as our targets for
potential short-term sell trades against
the overall direction that we initially
looked for from demand. So supply and
demand fails can actually be very
valuable because yes, while they
invalidate the first initial trade we
were looking for, they provide us with
these secondary opportunities. We can
flip the bias for the medium-term and
look for trades like this one. And when
we reach this area, that's where we can
start looking the other way once again.
All right, let's take a look at that
example of that demand fail format in
action. So let's say we see this market
trading to the upside. We've seen it
sweep beneath these relative equal lows
just here. And we're looking to buy. We
want to take a buy on this market. So,
we're going to look at the last candle
before the impulse. And we're going to
use this as our demand area to buy from.
So, we may be looking for the market to
make a little shift to the upside to
validate. Well, in this case, it's going
to be around this structural point to
validate a new high so that we can join
this trend. So, our current idea is to
look for a push higher and then buy on
the pullback like this. That is a good
way to set up a trade. But if we see the
market come down, fail to provide this
break up and actually break to the
downside, well, what this does is
actually just continues the downward
price action that we're currently seeing
here. And by failing at this demand, not
only do we invalidate the buy, so we
manage to get away with no trade here
instead of a loss, we actually lead into
possible sells because if we think about
what demand shows, it's that large push
of buying from this price level. So
therefore, we see this price area as the
discounted price to buy from. But when
the market doesn't react there, it tells
us that traders are not feeling that
anymore. We're not seeing institutional
participants come in with that
willingness to buy that they had
previously. So what we can actually do
is then look for possibility to trade
down towards new areas of demand. Now if
we look at these areas here, these have
all been retested. Every time we create
demand, the wick has come back and
retested it. So these are not areas we'd
be expecting to see a reversal again cuz
areas that have already been hit, a
demand zone that's already been tapped
is not a demand zone we want to look at.
Now, there's more context around that
thought in a little bit when we look at
how to forecast demand breaks or demand
fails before they occur. But for now,
the next open demand, the next point
with any imbalance is going to be the
demand right down here that we call this
the extreme demand cuz it's the furthest
in the price movement. It's the lowest
possible one. So now we have the
understanding that given that we've
broken through this demand, we are
likely to continue trading lower towards
the next demand. The demand here has
failed. There's no meaningful points
between where we are right now and this
lower demand where we're likely to see a
new influx of buying. Now, when we
consider this demand down here, we know
this was seen as a discounted price to
buy from. Okay, hence the impulsive move
that took place after this small
consolidation. Therefore, if we are
going to see another influx of buying,
it's likely to take place from here,
which pretty much leaves an open range
from where we are now all the way down
there, where there isn't really any push
back from buyers. So, what we could
actually do here is look at selling the
existing supply that we've come into and
we could target that demand zone for a
trade. So an idea of a position could be
something like this where what we're
actually doing is taking advantage of
the fact this demand has failed to hold
and now instead we're looking to
continue selling in line with what is
currently on this more refined view the
predominant trend which is down and then
we would look to take the market down to
this demand get out and that is where we
could look for the next possible buys or
if we don't get a buy from there and we
get a demand fail well simply we can
look to the left and take a look at
lower price areas which in this chart we
have quite a ways down to identify the
next possible point that the market
could lead into. So we treat these
supply and demand zones as kind of
levels for flips, right? Yes, we
initially want to buy from there because
we are moving with this larger uptrend.
But when we see there is no reaction
from it and when we see the market
breaking down instead, well, that opens
doors to very clear possibility for us
to use this as a pretty much forecast or
prediction that the market is now likely
to go lower. If the market was going to
go higher, it would have done so by
reacting from demand. But because we
didn't see a reaction from demand, and
because we've now broken lower, we can
continue moving with that overall market
flow, that overall direction, and
finalize that move to the next demand.
And that would be how we trade supply
and demand fails. So you don't only have
to rely on demand zones to provide the
confirmation you want for buy trades,
but you can also look at them as a way
of providing confirmation if the market
melts down instead. Right now, let's
take a look at an example the other way
with a supply fail. What we've got here
is a market that is moving to the
downside, creating lower lows and lower
highs. Our next selling point if we
wanted to sell into this market would be
from this supply zone just here which is
going to be the supply zone that's just
above price. So a selling move could
look like this. However, you see the
market comes through and then actually
breaks above this supply zone which
actually then creates a supply fail
here. This supply has now failed. Now
our next movement would then be to look
for imbalances and the next area of
potential supply that the market could
react from. We have imbalance that leads
all the way up. Potential supply there,
but we've got equal high liquidity.
These 1 2 3 4 points there, which means
we wouldn't look at this supply. We
would instead look at least at the
supply zone just above. So our next
potential supply for reversals if this
market is going to go bearish is going
to be there. Essentially, by creating
this high and creating this supply fail,
we've opened the doors to at least
trading through this range into this
area here before we then get any further
sell-offs if that is what we do. So, we
create a situation where now we can say,
okay, the safe thing to do, the obvious
thing to do is going to be buying from
this area of demand because the market
has somewhat shifted, even if it is
inside of an internal range. And then
when we get into here, we can assess
that for reversals and either go short
or if we again break through. Well, then
we have continued buying potential
through to the next supply. Okay, these
points here. So, what our trade would
look like then given that we've created
a supply fail would be to identify the
demand zone, which would be in this case
here just beneath the market gap. A gap
and an imbalance essentially are showing
the same thing. A gap though is just a
little bit stronger. When we see a gap,
it's highly likely to be filled. So, we
would place our buy there with our stops
beneath the zone and the targets could
easily go up to here. And this is a
situation where a supply fail, basically
a supply zone failing to hold and take
the market lower actually opens doors to
a pretty immediate buying opportunity.
As you can see, that follows through to
a profitable outcome trade. So, again,
this example flipped the other way. This
time, we're not looking at demand fails.
We're looking at supply fails. But all
we see is a zone that could potentially
cap price breaking which opens doors to
trading the other way. Basically range
to range through to the next point of
potential supply. And that movement
alone provides us with a trade which in
this case could have brought back 4% or
a little bit more in a very simple
format of just finalizing a buy into the
next supply before we then await the
next actions from the market. Now,
earlier on, I explained to you that you
can actually start to see demand and
supply fails before they've taken place,
which can be useful because it allows
you to catch early trades or it at least
lets you see where the market is likely
to go next to avoid taking trades in the
wrong direction and also set yourselves
up ahead of time so that you're ready to
pounce on the move. To explain the
auction theory in a quick sense, just as
a recap, we say that if we have a demand
zone like this with a large impulsive
buying move after it, it shows us that
the price range between here and here is
seen as a discount price for this asset.
So based on that theory, we expect if
the market gets back to this level
again, there's likely to be a good
influx of buying to take us into a new
high. That would be the demand zone
reacting as expected.
So given that we are generally expecting
fast movements to take place meaning we
may get one tap into this demand zone
and then a continuation higher. Now if
you take a look at what happened in this
zone we actually created the first tap
then we pushed up. We came back down for
a second tap and then we come back in
again for a third tap. Now what is this
telling us about this demand zone? Well,
by coming back in for a second and third
tap, we're seeing that the buying
pressure that's coming in from this
level is nowhere near as strong as it
used to be. When we saw the buying
pressure coming in from this level when
the zone was created, we saw a direct
push to the upside, a direct impulse
driving us into new highs. This time
though, we failed to get away and the
markets returned again. We've attempted
and failed to get away. So this is now
three taps, three attempts to go higher
and every single time up till now we
have failed which shows us that the
buying pressure inside of this range is
not strong. Okay, we don't have strong
buying pressure. So what can that tell
us then? Well, it tells us this demand
is no longer seen as a discount by as
many traders in as much force as it
previously was. Therefore, it gives us
insight into the fact that this market
may potentially go lower. So there's a
few ways we could set up here. The first
off is the more aggressive stance would
be to look for direct possibility to
sell down through the break. So you
could in an aggressive sense depending
on kind of how you trade look at a trade
from a supply zone to take us through
the demand and then into wherever we
wanted to go. That would be the first
and the most aggressive way to trade.
The second way to trade would be once
the demand fail actually comes through.
Then you can start looking at areas of
supply for the market to react from and
you could potentially look at selling
down once those reactions have come
through. Right? So if we followed that
through to where we are right now, we
see the demand officially failed in and
around this level. We then got a pull
back in to that area of supply and as of
the time of right now recording this
video, the market is on its way down
towards these lows. So there's two
potential trading opportunities. Number
one is aggressive. After the third tap
in, we start looking at opportunity to
sell down into the lows of the demand
fail. Following that, the less
aggressive stances. Once the demand fail
actually comes through, we immediately
position ourselves into shorts to bring
this market lower. both sides of this,
whichever way we're looking at it is
actually just basically identifying this
demand is very likely to go given that
it is being hit multiple times and
therefore positioning ourselves to
profit from when this market actually
does drive through demand. When the
demand fail becomes reality and the
market starts trading lower. Now, this
then opens doors to targeting lower
zones. As we've said, the lowest zone in
this market that we would then generally
look at as a target would be the area of
demand just here. This is going to be
the next demand. There's no real demand
zone inside of here. They've all been
retested by wicks. Therefore, seeing
one, two, three pushes into this low.
Gives us an insight that we can look for
selling potential to take us from this
existing range down towards the next
meaningful point of demand. Right? So,
the clearest way to identify supply and
demand fails before they occur is going
to be seeing multiple retests of the
same demand. Think of it like a wall.
And every time the market hits this
wall, it's hitting it with a hammer. If
we hit it once and bounce away, that's
great. But if we hit it a second time,
it's getting weaker. It will start to
crumble. We come in a third time and now
this wall is incredibly weak.
Eventually, it's going to break. If the
market, if the hammer keeps dropping on
this level, on this wall, it's going to
break eventually, which will lead us
through to lower prices, which is where
we manage to profit by, of course,
joining this and understanding that
direction either before or at the
earliest possible stages of this break
taking place. All right, so here's a
potential opportunity on GBP JPY. We
started to see the market breaking lower
from this high up here. We had a supply
zone retested, sell-off, creation of a
new supply zone, and now we've come in
and retested this. Now, if we let this
market run forward, of course, what we
would ideally want to see would be a big
run lower to create a new bearish
impulse. Given it some time, we do get a
nice trade to the downside. We fail to
make a new low, though, and then we
actually come in for a second tap. Now
again from what we've just discussed
this makes this zone weaker cuz every
time the market comes and hits this zone
again we are seeing that the sellers in
here and in here and now in here are not
coming in in as much force as they were
back here where we managed to create an
impulsive move to the downside. As you
can see as well this push has created a
closure very high to the top of the zone
which tells us that buyers at this point
are stronger than they've been at any
point through this supply. If you think
about where this bullish candle closed,
that shows buyers have managed to get
the market up here with some
sustainability, which they never managed
to do at any of these previous points.
That shows again buyer control, really
pushing against this supply. So, this is
a supply zone that actually becomes
better as a buying opportunity now than
a selling opportunity. We're in a
position where we've created demand
here, pushed away, pulled back. We could
happily look at buying the market from
this point and looking to take it
higher. I mean, realistically in this
kind of market, we would just want to
take it towards the next open point of
supply like this. So, you'd work inside
of the current trading range of where
we've come into basically this larger
unrefined area of demand. You'd look
inside of there for your refined
opportunity to buy this market up
towards that high. Right? This one would
be, I would say, less aggressive.
Although we don't actually have the full
supply fail yet, this is as good as
seeing that when we have a bullish
closure that is so high to the top of a
supply zone. In fact, the highest we've
seen throughout the entire duration of
the supply zone failures to go lower and
multiple pushes into that area of
supply, building strength every time.
That's a very high probability chance
then that we're actually likely to end
up breaking above. When we've broken
above, we can again look at continuation
possibility from areas of demand.
Basically refining again inside of this
price action and looking to buy once the
market returns to that level to take us
up to, of course, as we've said, next
points of open supply. So when we see
multiple taps into a supply, okay, one,
two, three, we're seeing continued
weakness here, which is therefore likely
to lead into continuations to the upside
rather than the good strong sell to the
downside, which of course is a little
bit crazy because when we see supply, we
generally expect to sell that. But this
is a very clear sign when we see these
market levels hit multiple times.
Essentially, just think of the context
of what this is truly showing you, which
is showing you selling pressure is not
so strong. Buying pressure is actually
building up against this level.
Therefore, our supply zone that we
initially thought was good may actually
be better as a flip into some buys. So,
to sum up, demand and supply fails in a
nutshell. Demand zones are areas of
significant buying power. And what we're
looking for is a reaction and
continuation to the upside. If we don't
see that given an immediate break, for
example, we would then use this demand
fail as an opportunity to sell down
towards lower points of demand or other
target areas. Now, if we do see an
initial reaction, but it doesn't manage
to make much ground in the market, and
we see multiple taps coming back in to
this same level, every one of these taps
weakens the zone and gives us an insight
that the next likely movement could be a
downward move, which allows us to sell
early into the move as we start to see
this zone being hit multiple times, or
just gives us insight that this is
likely to go and allows us to prime
setups that are ready to be executed if
we see that first demand fail. The same
exact format is true for supply zones.
If we see supply zone fails, that leads
into trades higher into higher areas of
supply. And if we see a supply zone hit
multiple times, well, that opens the
doors to an understanding that the next
likely move is going to be a buy, not a
sell.